<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Off the Blueprint</title>
    <description>Minimalist Packing, Train Travel, Independent Travel</description>
    <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://offtheblueprint.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 16:49:01 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 16:49:01 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Interview with Montréal-Based Travel Blogger Jennifer Doré Dallas (Moi, Mes Souliers)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/301137_10150753066790364_8027002_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jennifer Dore Dallas - Moi, Mes Souliers&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-1036&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met Jennifer at WordCamp Montréal this summer and really enjoyed talking to her about travel and packing, so I asked if I could interview her to learn more about her travel experiences. Her blog, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moimessouliers.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moi, mes souliers&lt;/a&gt;, is a thoughtful and comprehensive guide to traveling anywhere and she&#39;s been called one of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fredericgonzalo.com/en/2014/08/21/top-travel-bloggers-in-quebec/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;top travel bloggers in Québec&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: You’ve traveled all over the world, to over 35 countries. What do you hope to experience when you arrive in a new place?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Hum, it’s hard to describe. Every place is different and you travel to each and every one with a different expectation, but I always try to keep them low. This way, I’m almost always surprised and amazed by at least a few aspects of the place. I generally hope to find colourful photogenic spots, some awesome food I can try out and definitely markets. I love those!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: What did you enjoy about travel when you first started, and what do you enjoy about travel now?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: I think at first travel was a way for me to show I was free, I could be independent and I actually could show others I could make it. After my first big solo trip (2-month trip around Germany and surrounding capitals), it morphed into fascination at being constantly surprised, confronted with my own thoughts and values, seeing life is different everywhere and happiness isn’t always what you would expect! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for now, I’d say I enjoy people the most. I travel slower, look forward to meeting locals, discovering their life, their way of thinking, much more than seeing all the sights. I know, that sounds corny, but it’s true!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_8205.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jennifer Dore Dallas - Moi, Mes Souliers&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-1037&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: How much planning goes into each trip you take? What tools do you use to research trips?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Wow, if I’d had answered this 10 years ago, you’d have laughed at me for sure. I used to create Excel spreadsheets with tons of info, places to see, times I thought it would take to see them so I could cram as much I could in when visiting a city or country. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, planning revolves more and more around the time I have beforehand. I like to read a guidebook and a few blogposts about the place I’m going to, make sure I know what to expect in general, and then I let spontaneity do the rest. The less I plan, the more I enjoy my trip, although I do plan certain things in a global manner, like the cities I want to see and the first few nights where I’m going to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: How has travel changed your view of the world?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: I’m much more open-minded. I try to understand where people are coming from before I judge them. Not everything works like it does here in Quebec and that’s what makes the world go round. I appreciate even more what I do have!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: How did you build a business around your travel blog?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Hard question! For one, it sure doesn’t come overnight. I started &lt;a href=&quot;http://moimessouliers.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;moimessouliers.org&lt;/a&gt; for fun because I loved to write and wanted to share my love of travel. Soon, the corporate world I was in didn’t fulfill my needs and couldn’t bring me happiness any longer, so I decided to drop out and chase my dream to be a freelancer. The blog now is at the center of that life, but I can’t say it’s my sole income. I translate, copywrite, write for different blogs and publications, consult on my former IT experience, work as a community manager, etc. My travel blog has become like my resume, people know me because of it and it brings me awesome opportunities, but as many bloggers will tell you, it’s really hard to make a living off of blogging without having any sidelines. I wouldn’t change it for the world though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: What are the challenges you face working on the road and traveling constantly?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: I am a little different from typical digital nomads, as I have a home base where my fiancé is, in Montreal. I’m sometimes on the road for months at a time, but I’m also home for long periods as well. Let’s just say you absolutely need a good day planner to survive all the dates to remember! :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge I would say is Wi-Fi! Not everyone understands the importance of it for digital freelancers. It’s like a drug and although it might be strong enough for travelers to check their email, it might just not cut it when I need to upload photos to my Google Drive, making me want to pull my hair out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/photo-3-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jennifer Dore Dallas - Moi, Mes Souliers&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-1038&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: You’re fluent in both English and French. Why did you choose to blog in French? Do you have any suggestions for how English-speaking travel bloggers can do a better job of connecting with bloggers who write in other languages?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Indeed! My mom is a French-Quebecer and my dad an English-Quebecer, so I couldn’t really tell you what my mother tongue is, but I did go to school in French. I chose to blog in French because researching information in that language on the Web five years ago was such a hassle. I either found blogs from France, Belgium or Switzerland or had to revert to searching in English. It seemed information for Quebec readers was just non-existent, so I decided to fill that gap as best I could!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for suggestions, it’s hard to say. I think basically being open to the reality that although English is the main blogging and travel language, other worlds exist and we can very easily cohabitate would be a good start. Guest interviews like these help bridge the gap! :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: Although you’ve been all over the world, you still write about your travel discoveries here in your hometown. What Quebec sights or places still amaze you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Gosh! I love my city (Montreal) and the province of Quebec. The more I travel, the more I realize we have nothing to worry about on the touristic side. We have such a beautiful offer for visitors, we just have to keep putting the word out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite place in Montreal would have to be the Villeray neighborhood where I live. It’s up and coming and has changed so much in the past few years. Right along the Jean-Talon market, head out into the streets on the north side. You’ll hit Castelnau and Villeray streets where coffee shops, ice cream parlours, funky like design shops and other treasures are sure to make great stops. You can even rest in Jarry Park or go for a swim. I just LOVE it and a lot of tourists take photos of the spiral staircases here too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: What backpack do you currently travel with, and what’s in it? How did you decide what to pack?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: My backpack is an old bag from Trekk (the company doesn’t even exist anymore!). It’s huge, 80 litres, which I would never recommend to anyone, but at the time it seemed so small for all my possessions. I use it really often and never fill it (max 50-60%), but it’s practical when I want to bring back souvenirs! In it, you can find boatloads of Ziploc bags, packing cubes, too many wires for all my tech gear and some clothes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my trip, it took me ages to decide what to pack, it’s so hard to choose because I was travelling to many different countries with four different seasons. I ended up going for the essentials I knew I couldn’t find elsewhere and I think I did a pretty good job at limiting everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: In what ways has packing light changed your travel experience?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: Limiting your belongings on the road makes such a difference. Although my daypack is always heavy because I need to travel with my computer and DSLR for work, my backpack or suitcase gets lighter every single time I leave home. Easier to lug around, makes me more mobile, and I can run to catch trains if needed! I can also be patient when looking for accommodation as I can walk around longer without my back and shoulders hurting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OtB: Tell me about a trip you’re planning that you’re really excited about.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MMS: My next trip is to the Magdalen Islands, one of the most beautiful places on earth. I went there for the first time last year and fell in love. I can’t wait to go back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I’ll be flying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://tbexcon.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TBEX&lt;/a&gt; in Fort Lauderdale, a travel blogger conference and right after, to San Diego. A friend and I will drive the coast from there to Sonoma Valley and San Francisco. I’m stoked, can’t wait to see those views!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All photos in this post courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moimessouliers.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moi, mes souliers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 06:10:12 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/interviews/interview-with-montreal-based-travel-blogger-jennifer-dore-dallas-moi-mes-souliers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/interviews/interview-with-montreal-based-travel-blogger-jennifer-dore-dallas-moi-mes-souliers/</guid>
        
        <category>interview</category>
        
        <category>moi mes souliers</category>
        
        <category>montreal</category>
        
        <category>packing light</category>
        
        <category>quebec</category>
        
        <category>travel blogging</category>
        
        
        <category>Interviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Keeping it Cheap: Universal Studios-Singapore</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-433&quot; src=&quot;/assets/melissa_universal.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you&#39;ve been traveling through Southeast Asia and you&#39;ve saved a little extra cash to have a civilization break in Singapore.  Functioning wi-fi, ubiquitous western food, and a trip to a theme park is on the menu for the next few days.  Ahhhhh, how sweet it is to be able to drink water out of the tap, have ice in your Big Gulp and speak to the locals in English (and actually have them understand you).  The ticket to Universal Studios is a bit pricey for your budget, but you only live once.  However, as far as this theme park is concerned, the ticket is only the tip of the iceberg.  Once they get you through the gate, they want you to spend as much as possible and they&#39;ve hidden little costs around the park to keep your wallet hemorrhaging Sing dollars.  This article is to give fair warning to any budget conscious traveler like myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tickets&lt;/strong&gt;--Ticket prices vary throughout the year and it&#39;s best to avoid the peak season (Mid-November to the end of the year).  Stay away during weekends and holidays.   Not only do prices go up, but the place is packed.  Tickets are always cheaper on the weekday and you can purchase them in advance at 7-11 with no additional charge.  Remember!  You want to get there as soon as the park opens to get to the popular rides  and the ticket lines can be long even on a weekday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water&lt;/strong&gt;-The good news is that most of the waiting for rides is done in shade or inside a large building.  The bad news is that most of the walking paths are not protected from the Malaysian sun.  Plan way ahead to bring a good-sized bottle of water with you to the park.  Get it when you leave the guesthouse in the morning because once you reach Harborfront or Sentosa the price of a small bottle of water goes up astronomically.  Now, in the park, there are water fountains.  You can refill here as well as get a sadistic chuckle out of watching the Malaysians or PRC Chinese try to figure out how to use the darn things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roller Coasters&lt;/strong&gt;-  They don&#39;t allow loose articles on roller coasters (Battlestar Galactica, The Mummy). You have to put your bags, hats, sunglasses, and wallets into a locker which is only free for the first half-hour. BOO!  After that, it&#39;s two dollars every half-hour with a limit of 20 dollars.  When the park gets crowded in the afternoon, the first hour is free, etc.  Either you run back and switch lockers after every ride, which is what my friend and I did, or you end up paying a lot of extra money depending on how many times you want to ride.  It is possible to get through the line a little faster if you opt for the single-rider lane, but you and your buddies could end up finishing at different times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food&lt;/strong&gt;-  Do you want to eat cheaply?  Then don&#39;t buy anything in the park!  I know the popcorn smells tempting and the kiddies look happy with their ice cream, but show a little self-discipline and wait on that stuff until you get back to the 7-11 near your hostel!  There is a Malaysian-style hawker market just outside of the park and the prices are reasonable.  After you&#39;ve had your fill of G-forces and have cooled down in the Shrek 4D experience, you&#39;re energy reserves will be low and the Hainanese-style chicken and rice will hit the spot.  Just make sure that you get your hand stamped upon leaving the park so that you can get back in.  Also, consider getting an ice coffee at the kopitiam.  The combination of sugar and caffeine will give you one last boost of energy to go queue for the Transformers ride again.  Speaking from personal experience, this ride is much much better during a caffeine high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoying your day at Universal Studios doesn&#39;t have to deplete your budget.  This is information I wish that someone had given me before I went to the park.  If you plan properly, it&#39;s a great experience and it&#39;ll give you bragging rights at the next hostel on the backpacker trail.  &quot;Who cares if you got to go to Uluru!  I got to go to Universal Studios.  You got to see an old aborigine.  I got to see Optimus Prime!&quot;  Have fun &quot;riding the movies&quot;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 20:50:09 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/universal-studios-singapore-tips-for-the-budget-traveler/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/universal-studios-singapore-tips-for-the-budget-traveler/</guid>
        
        <category>backpacking</category>
        
        <category>budget</category>
        
        <category>roller coaster</category>
        
        <category>Singapore</category>
        
        <category>Universal Studios</category>
        
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Caged In, Flying Free</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/abi_bike.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;abi_bike&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-417&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 14, I clipped my bags to my rack, swung my leg over my seat, and slid my feet into my pedal cages. I was about to start the journey of a lifetime: a bike ride from the east coast of Virginia to the west coast of Oregon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began planning the trip about a year before I set out. My friends and family didn’t believe that I’d actually follow through when I first revealed my idea (I’d always had adventure pipe-dreams). But this idea was bigger, and more real. I was determined to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A stressful year full of thesis-writing and nagging (“So what next? Any job prospects? What are you going to do with your life?”) threatened me with the undesirable prospect of “growing up,” but after my diploma was placed in my hand on that hot May day, I took my own unconventional leap into “adulthood.” A day and a half later, I was saying goodbye to my parents at the mouth of the James River in Yorktown, Va.--packed but not prepared. I hadn’t processed college graduation or done much physical training, but, ready or not, I was about to fill my lungs with adventure, raw and wonderful. At that stage, I couldn’t even fathom the experiences lying before me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_3338-1024x764.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;IMG_3338&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-401&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next 2 and half months, I lived radically differently than I had the previous 21 years of my life. I rode my bike an average of 65 miles each day, carried my entire livelihood in two saddlebags, met new people at every pit stop, and called a new patch of grass or bit of church floor my home each night. The trip was as romantic and freeing as it sounds, maybe more so. For the first time in so long, I didn’t need to worry about meeting deadlines, finishing coursework, dealing with “friend drama,” or even what I should wear. I had two riding outfits, two t-shirts for wearing off the bike, no mirror, and zero makeup (not even legitimate facewash). This simplicity allowed me to truly detach myself from superficial concerns and gaze outwardly at the unembellished, inspiring beauty of the country I had lived in my whole life but barely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_3953-1024x764.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;IMG_3953&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-402&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_4170-1024x764.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;IMG_4170&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-403&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had no idea in setting out just how much I would gain from this trip; I only knew it would be a great adventure and it would change me. How right I was! But how much that actually meant, I could not have known. I think it is significant that I was not mentally or physically ready for this undertaking but went anyway. When in life are we actually ready for what is thrown at us? But should this stop us from acting? No! You must, as Mark Twain so perfectly states, “throw off the bowlines. Sail away from the safe harbor. Catch the trade winds in your sails. Explore. Dream. Discover.” Without a healthy dose of uncertainty, how can we learn or accomplish things we never thought possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished my journey with over 4250 miles of road under my tires, some wicked tan lines, and an increased thirst for adventure. I still didn’t know what my future held, but I had confidence in myself like never before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_4203-1024x764.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;IMG_4203&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-404&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2012 07:06:42 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/bike%20travel/caged-in-flying-free/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/bike%20travel/caged-in-flying-free/</guid>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
        <category>bike trip</category>
        
        <category>cross country</category>
        
        <category>cycling</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        
        <category>Bike Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tips for Living Like a Gourmet Without Ice or Refrigeration</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Have you ever wondered how you’re going to store food when the grid fails during the apocalypse? But even more pressingly, do you know how to eat well during the inevitable post-storm power outages in your neighborhood? In my experience, while the power company spends its energies hooking up more important buildings like schools and hospitals, I spend at least the first day in the dark.  That means encouraging my family to eat ice cream before it melts and cooking hot dogs over a fire. The fridge’s cold air is fading fast and it can only be opened on a strict schedule: whenever every member of the family is simultaneously dying of hunger. By the second day, the refrigerator’s cooling powers have failed entirely. The now useless box begins to stink of rot and breakfast is served at the donut store. In fact, every meal is either pizza or donuts until the electric company decides to grace my street with their omnipotent presence. Although a power outage is a kid’s culinary dream, it can be an adult&#39;s nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, with a little knowledge and planning, you can actually cook delicious meals without a refrigerator. After living on boats for almost four years with no or limited electricity, I have learned it is possible to eat like a gourmet without ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-386&quot; src=&quot;/assets/IMG_36263-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;  /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a gas stove:&lt;/strong&gt; With a gas-powered stove, you can heat basics like hot water even when there’s no electricity. Boiled water will be vital after the apocalypse when there is no clean, running water.  Just kidding.. sort of.  If your main stove is electric, a small camp stove with a propane tank will suffice for roughing it during a power outage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eggs Eggs Eggs!!!&lt;/strong&gt; Eggs don’t need to be refrigerated! Eggs can last up to a month at room temperature. You do need to turn them over every day to coat the insides of the shell with yolk. Otherwise, the shells will become brittle and crack more easily. If they smell bad, or are cracked toss them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canned Food:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Canned beans and veggies are a great way to store food. These can go great in soups, chilies, and stews, or make a nice addition to salad. Be sure to have a non-electric can opener.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fresh Vegetables:&lt;/strong&gt; Many vegetables do not need refrigeration. Root vegetables such as onions, carrots, and potatoes can last for weeks in a cool, dark area. More perishable vegetables, like tomatoes and zucchini, can last a week in room temperature conditions.  Tomatoes even taste better when they’re not refrigerated. Use your judgement when storing food. Of course, vegetables will last longer in cool, dark places. If you live in Alaska, your food will last longer than in Jamaica. I would recommend going vegetable shopping twice a week to keep up a rotation of your stores.  Now you can make onion, garlic, and tomato egg omelets!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fresh Fruit:&lt;/strong&gt; Most fruits do not need refrigeration. Apples, bananas, and oranges will all do fine for weeks without refrigeration. Store apples away from other fruits, however, because they have a tendency to cause other produce to decay more rapidly. Berries and peaches will last a few days without refrigeration. Don&#39;t eat if they are moldy! Again, shop for these more perishable fruits a few times a week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dairy Products:&lt;/strong&gt; Butter can last weeks without refrigeration. Monitor the butter for spoil. To encourage your cheese to last indefinitely out of the fridge, wrap hard cheeses in vinegar and cheese cloths. This may prolong the life of your cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rice:&lt;/strong&gt; and other grains are perfect when you have limited power. If you have your gas stove, you can cook up a pot of rice, and add some of your fresh veggies for a great dinner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Become a Vegetarian:&lt;/strong&gt; I would not advise storing meat when you do not have refrigeration or an ice box. If you must have meat, cured sausages such as charcuterie will keep without refrigeration. Canned fish is a great way to add protein. If you really enjoy the 19th century lifestyle, salted cod will also keep. Soak the dried, salted fillet in water for a day, and you will have fresh, desalted, re-hydrated fish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beverages:&lt;/strong&gt; Wine and beer store nicely and will go well with your preserved cheese! Enjoy your next power outage in French style!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/lunch1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-385 &quot; src=&quot;/assets/lunch1-300x219.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please use your own judgement when consuming any food. These are techniques the author has found useful. The author is not liable for any illnesses you may experience due to eating non refrigerated food.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2012 12:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/boat%20life/tips-for-living-like-a-gourmet-without-ice-or-refrigeration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/boat%20life/tips-for-living-like-a-gourmet-without-ice-or-refrigeration/</guid>
        
        <category>off the grid</category>
        
        <category>Survival</category>
        
        
        <category>Boat Life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chasing Butterflies into Traffic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chasing_butterflies.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;River Kwai at Sunset&quot; title=&quot;River Kwai at Sunset&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-360&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;I was in Kanchanaburi, Thailand, and I hadn&#39;t been sleeping well. The walls of my hostel room looked solid, but I was pretty sure they were actually painted paper. My neighbors might as well have been making their late night calls in there with me. Still, for 300 THB (around $10) a night, I could live with it. I just hoped that no one was around the night before, when I had belted out that Air Supply tune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify&quot;&gt;I&#39;ve heard Thailand described as &quot;International Travel 101&quot; because it&#39;s a country where one can easily travel by bus or train, many people speak English, it&#39;s inexpensive, and it&#39;s relatively safe for a single female adventurer. More importantly, it&#39;s so far removed from anything that one could experience in the Midwest. I was a novice traveler who wanted a taste of the exotic, but with a safety-net. This was Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/001-768x1024.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hellfire Pass&quot; title=&quot;Hellfire Pass&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-331&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;My plan for the day was to hike along Hellfire Pass, where the Japanese forced Allied POWs to cut through rocky hillside to lay dow railroad tracks during World War II. Most tourists join a day tour to do this. They climb into an air-conditioned van to go to the pass and at least one other destination, such as Sai Yok Noi Falls or the Tiger Temple. I had no interest in the Falls or the Temple, so I shunned all of the package tours. Besides, they didn&#39;t include a ride on the famous &quot;Death Train&quot; -- the Thailand-Burma Railway built by Japan -- or the chance to cross the equally famous bridge over the River Kwai. There was no way I was missing those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because they are subject to the schedule of the day tours, many tourists only get to see the visitor center and the first section of track at Hellfire Pass. Apart from being in Nam Tok by 2:00pm to catch the Death Train, my schedule was my own. I could take my time exploring the extra three kilometers accessible to hikers. I continued to the next spot on the line where the rock had to be cut to lay down track, not nearly as deep as Hellfire Pass, but deep enough to feel like a tomb. I took all the historical information I had gleaned from various sources and allowed my imagination to conjure up scenes of overworked, undernourished POWs subjected to brutal working conditions so that the Japanese engineers could make their deadlines. Emaciated figures casting demonic-shaped shadows on the walls of rock as they work into the night by firelight. The teeth-gnashing sound of metal striking rock, and the heart-rending atmosphere of the human spirit trying to endure long after the body is ready to call it quits. After a few minutes in this world, I was sufficiently spooked to do an about-face and head back to the visitors center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;And what of the captors? When I had visited Thailand-Burma railway museum a few days before, I&#39;d seen a video that included an interview with one of the Japanese engineers who worked on the River Kwai bridge. He didn’t seem to feel any remorse. He didn’t say that he was under orders. His only comment had to do with an inaccuracy in the film version of the story. He wanted to let the record show that the Japanese engineers did not consult the expertise of the British engineers while building the Bridge on the River Kwai. The mere suggestion outraged him. Incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/0011.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;POW cemetery in Kanchanaburi&quot; title=&quot;POW cemetery in Kanchanaburi&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-343&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Hellfire pass is in the middle of nowhere, so to get to Nam Tok requires backtracking about 20 kilometers. There&#39;s no defined bus stop outside of the visitor’s center, but it’s along a road that’s used by many buses to do the Kanchanaburi-Sangkhlaburi run. I knew that I wouldn’t be waiting for a ride for very long. Still, ten minutes in mid-day Thailand heat can feel like an eternity. There was a small patch of shade close by, but some Thai women with a tamarind stand had already claimed it as their own. I hoped they would share it, but as I approached their conversation stopped and they glared at me. I had no interest in purchasing tamarind, so I felt very unwelcome. Somewhere a loudspeaker was playing a Thai pop song. It was like a rasp to my nerves. I decided to walk in the direction of Nam Tok, if anything to get away from that music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;I was walking for about five minutes when a truck pulled over. The driver asked me where I was going and I told him my destination. He offered me a ride to Nam Tok. I asked him how much he wanted. He said he would do it for free. I was 99% sure that nothing would happen if I got in that truck, but it was that nagging 1% that made me decline his offer. I felt bad about insulting him, but if he had a wife or daughters, I’m sure he understood. Besides, even with my limited experience I knew that nothing in Asia is free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;I only had to walk another five minutes before I was able to flag down a passing bus. They asked for 5 THB to get to Nam Tok, and I was happy to hand it over. I had a moment of self-congratulations. I pitied the folks on the package tours. They had to pay so much and visit places they didn&#39;t want to go. I patted my own back again when I successfully found the Nam Tok train station. It&#39;s not too far off of the main road and there is a sign that points the way. I arrived on time, but, in true Thai fashion, the train was more than 40 minutes late. I had to wait on the platform with several hundred primary school students who were on an outing. They were full of energy, but well-behaved. “Hello” seemed to be the only word they knew in English, and I had to say it in reply about 50 or 60 times before I found a safe little hiding place behind a sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/0221-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fellow passengers on the &amp;quot;Death Train&amp;quot;&quot; title=&quot;Fellow passengers on the &amp;quot;Death Train&amp;quot;&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-339&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;The ride on the Death Train was very similar to other train rides I&#39;ve done in Thailand. You sit on hard, straight-backed seats, withering in the heat as food, drink and useless trinket vendors move up and down the aisles. They drone on about their item in a melancholy Thai mantra as they bump past you for the umpteenth time. I was weary and irritable when we finally approached Kanchanaburi. I thought maybe I had been a bit hasty about disrespecting the package tours in their air-conditioned buses, but then the train stopped. We had come to the famous bridge. Everyone perked up to full attention, myself included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all gathered at the windows as the train slowly started rolling over the bridge. There were also tourists gathered at the far side of the bridge watching the train come in. They all cheered as the train cars passed. On the train, off the train everyone was waving and cheering. All of the day&#39;s frustrations melted away in an instant. The train pulled into the station at Kanchanaburi. I jumped onto the platform with renewed energy, my head held high and a smile on my face. I had successfully planned and executed a day trip in a foreign country with very little assistance. Me, a novice traveler. The kid my mother always worried about wandering into traffic while chasing a butterfly. I had a bounce in my step as I walked back to my painted-paper wall hostel, visions of future travel adventures unfolding in my mind’s eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/049-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Of course, Kanachanaburi has more to offer than a history lesson....&quot; title=&quot;Of course, Kanachanaburi has more to offer than a history lesson....&quot;  /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 22:18:38 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/chasing-butterflies-into-traffic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/chasing-butterflies-into-traffic/</guid>
        
        <category>backpacking</category>
        
        <category>independent travel</category>
        
        <category>River Kwai</category>
        
        <category>Thailand</category>
        
        <category>WWII history</category>
        
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Awakening at Tiananmen Square</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/IMG_18201.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-206&quot; src=&quot;/assets/IMG_18201-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Flag raising at dawn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cool October morning air made me thankful that I had brought a jacket with me to Beijing. I hadn’t needed it in the daytime, but in the pre-dawn hours it was a necessity. I took a look around to see who else was out and about at this time of day. It was mostly plainly-dressed people who looked as though they had more important things to do than mess with me. I had been in China’s capital for over a week studying Mandarin, but my defenses were still on high-alert. There’s no class or guidebook that can prepare you for your first adventure in a strange land, and each day was another dose of culture shock. I’d been lured out of my safe Kansas suburb by the “learn Chinese in China” promise, and my safe if quirky hobby had suddenly become a full-blown pilgrimage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why I thought the metro would be open that early. The gates were locked and the sign for hours of operation told me that if I waited for the metro to open I wouldn’t make it to Tiananmen Square in time for the flag raising. The distance was too far to walk and I had no clue about city buses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That left one option. The dreaded option. I would have to take a taxi. I quickly walked to an intersection and timidly put out my hand, cringing back as though the crazy Beijing traffic might leave it a bloody stump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had developed an aversion to Chinese cab drivers a week earlier, when a group of us had been conned into paying way too much for a ride to the Great Wall. It was a classic rookie mistake. Were we supposed to haggle on the price? Absolutely. Did we know that we were supposed to haggle? Definitely not, and I’d only realized our mistake after we’d paid the money and hopped into the minivan. We didn’t lose too much money, but I always hate feeling like a chump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this occasion, I could see that the cabbie who had stopped for me had a meter. Hoorah! No haggling necessary! I was so excited that I banged my head jumping into the taxi. After the stars went away I noticed the driver looking at me. Meiyou wenti, I said: no problem, I’m fine! But then I realized that he wasn’t looking at me out of concern. He needed a destination. With one hand on my head and one hand pointing forward, I wearily said “Tiananmen Square” like a wounded general leading his troops into battle. As we rode to the famous square, I kept a very close eye on the meter, making sure that the fare added up correctly. I watched the driver too to make sure that he didn’t put some cab driver “hoodoo” on the little machine to make it multiply or jump to the RMB equivalent of Bolivia’s GNP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/IMG_1831.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-207&quot; src=&quot;/assets/IMG_1831-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tiananmen Square&quot;  /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why I thought that I would be the only person in the square that morning, but again, I was wrong. No sign of sun yet and there was already a sizable crowd of patriotic Chinese citizens. I picked a spot on the shore of the human sea that I thought would have the best vantage point for pictures. More people arrived and swarmed around and behind me. Again, I was thankful for the jacket. I don’t like to have strangers touching my bare skin and the crowd was squeezing in. The man next to me must have been from an industrial town because he breathed with a horrible rattling wheeze. He was so close to me that every time he inhaled I could feel that rumble in his chest like it was my own. At one point, he tried to maneuver to get in front of me, but his small, Chinese, rice-fed physique was no match for an American, beef-fed, big-shouldered broad. I stood my ground with all of the resolve of an iron girder while ferociously minding the position of my bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I patiently waited for the first light of day. I could see the guard by the flag pole beginning to stir and I thought that this was a good sign. Another patriotic group began trying to maneuver their way in front of me, but this time it was a woman attempting to squeeze a little girl in a pink coat into a very small bubble in the human sea. The woman pushed the girl until she wailed in protest. Not even the small girl could squeeze through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the tint of the eastern sky went from black to sapphire. The guards lined up by the waiting flagpole. Camera flashes popped all around me and I thought, “Fools, you just got a nice shot of the guy’s head in front of you.” When the sapphire changed to a rosy purple, the guard slowly began the ceremony. There was no sound during the flag-raising, but when it reached its pinnacle the piercing music of the Chinese National Anthem played at a deafening level. I cringed, but as I looked around I realized everyone else had tears in their eyes. The solemnity of the crowd moved me as well as spooked me. They weren’t here to protest or to bicker over petty differences. They were here to salute their flag, to take pride in the fact that they were Chinese. I could physically feel the press of this tiny percentage of China, and I shivered as I imagined the immense power of a country 1.3 billion strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/IMG_1834.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-208&quot; src=&quot;/assets/IMG_1834-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;Tiananmen&amp;quot; in Chinese means &amp;quot;the gate of heavenly peace&amp;quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of a sudden, learning Mandarin didn’t seem like such a quirky activity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2012 13:09:06 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/awakening-at-tiananmen-square/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/awakening-at-tiananmen-square/</guid>
        
        <category>backpacking</category>
        
        <category>china</category>
        
        <category>culture shock</category>
        
        <category>independent travel</category>
        
        <category>languages</category>
        
        <category>mandarin</category>
        
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Traveling Thoughts</title>
        <description>&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/Morning-Walk15.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-255&quot; src=&quot;/assets/Morning-Walk15-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always had a certain sense of calm when traveling.  Even though the chaos of trying to catch the right flight or train or bus can be overwhelming, once you are actually in transit everything magically falls into place. Even if it is just for a few moments, there can be an immense feeling of comfort and security.  Time seems to stand still for those few minutes or hours. Nobody knows exactly where you are and, just for a little while you can forget every other sense responsibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was growing up in New York City, my daily subway rides to school were a way for me to steal some extra moments to simply close my eyes and rest before the chaos of another school day began.  I was grateful for the lack of responsibility in that moment. I could simply be. I didn&#39;t have to think about or do anything that I didn&#39;t want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember, my direction in life has always been a linear path towards a logical destination. Ever since I was a little kid my goal in life has been to be a doctor.  I have always been busy staying at the top of my class and planning ahead for that future. I went from a competitive high school to a prestigious college and then straight to medical school. It was during medical school that I noticed that I wasn’t happy following that path anymore. I was progressively getting more cynical and bitter. I could no longer sympathize with patients, and I was getting easily irritated when I talked to family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of me began to question why I was struggling and trying to make it to the end of medical school, the next step in a pre-programmed plan.  I couldn&#39;t seem to justify pushing myself further into such a demanding field when I felt so conflicted. Medical school became a frustrating journey to nowhere. I was lost and I didn&#39;t know where I wanted to go or what I wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was going through the motions of studying, taking tests and examining patients but my heart wasn&#39;t in it. I started resent of everyone who had ever encouraged me to pursue my dream of becoming a doctor. I started to resent everyone who couldn’t understand my unhappiness and tried to comfort me with their naïve glorified view of what it was to be a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I asked myself: how am I going to take care of sick patients when I couldn&#39;t even take care of myself? Who was going to take care of me if I decided to devote myself to the service of others? The answer that came to me was that I had to take responsibility for my own happiness.  I could feel the pressure getting to me more and more by the day and I knew that if not today then tomorrow, my frustration would reach a crisis point and I would completely abandon this pursuit that I had devoted my entire life to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only solution I could think was to take a break and find the way back to my happiness. Taking a step back and experiencing something completely different would release me from the repetitive mundane motions of everyday life. I took a leave of absence from school and made plans to travel. I hoped to once again experience that sense of calm that comes from being in transit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first stop in my travels was Laredo, Texas where I studied border medicine at the US-Mexico border. In Laredo, I experienced a completely new world. I was introduced to a unique combination of Southern culture and Mexican culture all at once. As the only female medical student joining a group of male preventive medicine residents, I also felt transported time of chivalry. I was away from all my family and friends but the group of residents and the program coordinators always took care of me and made sure I was doing okay. I appreciated being taken care of in a way that I never thought I would. My strong streak of independence was still alive but I couldn&#39;t help but be touched by genuine concern and care I experienced from everyone there. Every day I woke up to a new adventure. One day we would visit the local health department to learn about the unique diseases prevalent on the border. Another day we would go to a private ranch to learn about herbal medicine. Other days we would wade through the Rio Grande to test its waters for bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://offtheblueprint.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/025.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-256&quot; src=&quot;/assets/025-1024x768.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Hunting shed with equipment and relics of successful hunting expeditions on a ranch in Laredo, Texas&quot; alt=&quot;Hunting shed with equipment and relics of successful hunting expeditions on a ranch in Laredo, Texas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my plane ride back home from Texas, I was reading Thich Nhat Hanh&#39;s &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline&quot;&gt;Answers from the Heart&lt;/span&gt;, and he wrote something that resonated profoundly with me at that moment.&lt;em&gt; &quot;In order to make another person happy, you have to be happy yourself. So there&#39;s a link between doing and being. If you don&#39;t succeed in being, you can&#39;t succeed in doing. If you don&#39;t feel that you&#39;re on the right path, happiness isn’t possible. This is true for everyone; if you don&#39;t know where you&#39;re going, you suffer.&quot; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don&#39;t know where I am going or what my new direction in life is but as Hanh explains, all that matters is that you feel like you are on the right path to your destination. By living my life according to what makes me happy, I feel that I am much closer to getting to that right direction than I was a few months ago. Before I went to Texas, I was living the mundane ordinary life of a medical student. I was studying for an endless line of exams and working at the hospital at all hours of the day. After spending a month in Laredo, I was truly happy with my life. I was no longer simply on a linear path, blindly trying to make it to the end. I was now filled with a sense of freedom and happiness that I never expected to feel ever again.  While I have that sense of purpose, not only can I imagine gladly taking care of patients and becoming an excellent physician, but I can see myself turning into the type of person that I&#39;ve always aspired to be: happy, optimistic and able to live in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 18:55:48 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/happiness/my-traveling-thoughts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/happiness/my-traveling-thoughts/</guid>
        
        <category>career choices</category>
        
        <category>direction</category>
        
        <category>happiness</category>
        
        <category>medical school</category>
        
        <category>new york city</category>
        
        <category>texas</category>
        
        <category>transit</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        
        <category>Happiness</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Comic: A Short Discourse on Audioguides</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A short discourse on audio guides, narrated by myself. Click the image to read!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://morphmaker.deviantart.com/art/Discourse-on-Audio-Guides-301452069&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/audioguides_comic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Audioguides comic&quot; title=&quot;Audioguides comic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 08:18:17 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/comic-a-short-discourse-on-audioguides/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://offtheblueprint.com/travel/comic-a-short-discourse-on-audioguides/</guid>
        
        <category>comic</category>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
        
        <category>Travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
